Robert Garrett Collection of Ethiopic Magic Scrolls, 1700-1900: Finding Aid C0744.04
Manuscripts Division
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 17, 1850-1899; 17; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a very uneven and untutored hand (7-8mm). 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  - Prayer against "The Evil Eye, Headache and All Types of Disease", circa 1850-1899; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 18, 1700-1799; 18; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. The parchment has been carefully repaired before writing where a natural hole occurs. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a careful hand (4mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  Grid of 9 squares with a central face, and alternating transverse cruciform motifs and pairs of squares with circles at the center. (In ink with red and yellow color.
  Eight-pointed star design with central face. (In ink with red and yellow color.
  Grid of 9 squares with alternating eye-motif and chevron infill. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Owner: Wälättä Rufa'él (f.)
  - The Prayer of Susenyos for the Protection of Suckling Infants and Mothers Whose Infants Do Not Survive; Incorporating the Legend of Susenyos, 18th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Shotälay, 18th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic. Prayer for Driving Out Evil Spirits, 18th century; 1 item
    In continuo from preceding text.
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage in Women, 18th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage and Miscarriage, 18th century; 1 item
  - Prayers against Hemorrhage, etc. Sälam (Hymn Of Salutation) to Jesus' Side Pierced by the Spear of Longinus, 18th century; 1 item
    In continuo.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 19, 1800-1899; 19; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable hand (3-4mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 1 talismanic drawing and 1 chart. (Box 1)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with yellow wash and decoration in red.)
  Chart comprising a grid of 108 squares each containing the name of a "Hebrew" letter.
  Owner: Wälättä Heywät (f.)
  - Prayer for Blood Clotting (Märge'é Däm) and against Hemorrhage, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Miscarriage [Caused] by Barya, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayers for Successful Childbirth, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Barya and Légéwon, 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 20, 1770-1830; 20; 2 pieces of parchment sewn together; the top of the scroll is damaged and part is now missing. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable hand (3-4mm). 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  [now partly lost] Cross within a decorated frame.
  An equestrian saint spearing a prostrate figure beneath his horse (St. Susenyos slaying Werzelya).
  Three pairs of angelic figures arranged in rows one above the other: the first comprise winged torsos and heads; the second have their wings crossed in front of them; the third are holding drawn swords.
  Owner: the original owner's name, Wälättä Tensa'é (f.), has mostly been erased and replaced with that of Ta'ekä Maryam (f.)
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage and for Successful Pregnancy, Incorporating the Legend of Susenyos, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer for Successful Pregnancy and against Hemorrhage, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer against Barya and Légéwon. Prayer against Headache, Colic, Mäggañña and Gusemt, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 21, 1800-1850; 21; 2 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable hand (3-4mm), framed within an uncolored linear border. 3 talismanic drawings. Preserved within a leather cylinder pouch. (Box 1)
  Guardian angel with a drawn sword. (In ink with red, yellow and greenish brown color.
  Eight-pointed star design with central face; each of the arms of the star contains a protective eye motif. (In ink with red, yellow and greenish brown color
  Cross (in the form of a hand cross) with two stylized figures either side, the whole framed within a latticework border. (In ink with red, yellow and greenish brown color.)
  Owner: the original owner's name, Gäbrä Mäd[h]en (m.) has been mostly erased and replaced with that of Wâlättä Giyorgis (f.)
  - Prayer for the Binding of Demons (Ma'esäromu Lä'aganent), circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer against "All Diseases and All Ailments, All Impediments and All Dissention (Or Heresy) and Doubt, All Evil Spirits [That Cause] Deafness and Murder ...", circa 1800-1850; 1 item
    Without introduction or title.
  - Prayer against Nädära "Which Is the Evil Eye of Demons", circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer against "Foul Légéwon Who Cuts the Hearts of Men", circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer against Terror [delgasé (?) wädengas'é] of Demons, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 22, 1870-1930; 22; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together, with a tying string at the top. 1 col., written in black with rubrics (in purple ink, now faded and partly illegible) in a reasonable hand (3-4mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 4 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  Central lozenge with concentric circle decoration from the four sides of which extend four foliate arms. (In ink with some yellow and faded purple color.)
  An equestrian saint spearing a prostrate human figure beneath his horse (St. Susenyos slaying Werzelya). (In ink with yellow, black, grey and faded purple color.)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with yellow, black and faded purple color.)
  Cross (in hand cross form) with the sun and moon above.
  Owner: Wälättä Kidan (f.)
  - Prayer of Susenyos for the Protection of Suckling Infants and Their Mothers; Also Incorporated Are Supplications against Barya, Légéwon, Headache, Colic, Rheumatism, Sciatica, the Evil Eye, Stroke, Zar and Many Other Ailments, circa 1870-1930; 1 item
    Includes the beginning of the Legend of Susenyos.
  - Prayer for the Binding of Demons, circa 1870-1930; 1 item
  - Prayer against (Chest) Pain, circa 1870-1930; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 23, 1730-1770; 23; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a well-formed and regular hand (5-6mm). 3 finely executed talismanic drawings and 1 group of talismanic letters. (Box 1)
  [Now much rubbed and faded] Eight-pointed star design with central face. (In ink with yellow, red and blue color.)
  Series of concentric circles with central "sun face" motif, radiating 'rays' and stylized cloud design in the outermost circle. (In ink with red, yellow and dark blue-grey color.
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. The angel's cape is decorated with a repeat floral pattern typical of mid 18th century manuscript painting. He stands between two borders decorated with the same cloud design seen in the previous figure.
  A small group of talismanic letters and designs. (In ink, uncolored.)
  Owner: the original owner's name has been roughly erased throughout, but is just legible as Emnä S'eyon (f.)
  - The Prayer and Legend of Susenyos for Suckling Infants and Successful Pregnancy; Prayer "of the Strong and the Pregnant" (S'enu'an Wäs'enusat), for the Protection of Pregnant Women, mid 18th century; 1 item
    Includes a Sälam to Wäldä P'ét'ros Sosi (?).
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage, mid 18th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Shotälay, mid 18th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Légéwon, mid 18th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 24, 1800-1899; 24; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together and rolled from the top, with a tying string at the bottom. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a poor and uneven hand (5-6mm) with some blotting, illegible in places. The text is framed within a plain linear border. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  Guardian angel. (In ink with faded yellow and red color.
  Elongated derivative of the eight-pointed star design; at the center are four faces, and four of the arms of the star forming a cross shape are filled with intricate decoration. The text across the top of the design reads 'the seal of Alexander.'
  The figure of a saint mounted on, or standing behind a lion (St. Samuel ?)
  Owner: Wälättä Giyorgis (f.)
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya, Légéwon and Zar, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer of Susenyos for the Protection of Suckling Infants, etc, 19th century; 1 item
  - Invocation to Michael, Gabriel and Other Archangels, 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 25, 1830-1870; 25; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable hand (4mm), framed between a linear border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. Preserved within a leather cylinder pouch in two halves connected with a leather thong. (Box 1)
  Eight-pointed star design with lobed, eye-motif figures at the center and the four corners. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Another, different eight-pointed star design. (In ink with black, red and yellow color.)
  A third, different eight-pointed star design. (In ink with black, red and yellow color.)
  Owner: Wälättä Iyäsus (f.)
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya and Légéwon, Incorporating the Legend of Susenyos, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya, of Sorcerers and [aynä] T'ela, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Foul Légéwon, mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 26, 1870-1899; 26; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics (many evidently in Western ink ?), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with yellow, red and blue color.)
  Another guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with yellow, red and blue color.)
  Cross (in hand cross form) with highly stylized sun and moon above, two lobed figures either side and two undefined figures below – these may represent Mary and the Apostle John, who are frequently portrayed either side of the Cross, and the skulls or bodies of Adam and Eve, who are sometimes shown in traditional iconography at the foot of the Cross.
  Owner: Aqléseya Gäzzacchen (f.)
  - The Prayer of Susenyos against Infant Mortality, Incorporating the Legend of Susenyos, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Mäggañña, Shotälay, Buda, Blacksmiths, Ejjä säbe' (Craftsmen ?), Zar and Other Malicious Forces, Incorporating the Beginning of the Gospel of John, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Nädära, late 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 27, 1830-1870; 27; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together; the top of the scroll has been cut off. 2 cols., written in black with rubrics, now rather faded and in part illegible, in a small and tidy hand (2-3mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow with a similar yellow central margin. There are also 63 lines of text in a single col. on the obverse. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  A pair of guardian angels with drawn swords. (In ink with blue-grey, red and yellow color.)
  A further pair of guardian angels with drawn swords. (In ink with blue-grey, red and yellow color.)
  A single guardian angel with a drawn sword. (In ink with blue-grey, red and yellow color.)
  Owner: The original owner is Ar'ayä Sellasé (m.), but the name of Amätä Maryam (f.) has been inserted in some of the margins.
  - Prayers for the Drowning of Demons, Each According to the Seven Days of the Week, And Continuing With the Anathematizing of Demons by the Power of God and the Virgin Mary, mid 19th century; 1 item
    First part largely illegible, beginning in abrupto.
  - Prayer against the Evil eye. A Hymn and Sälam to the Archangel Phanuel, Continuing on the Obverse, mid 19th century; 1 item
    Largely illegible.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 28, 1800-1868; 28; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. The top of the scroll is damaged and a small part is now missing. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a well-formed and compact hand (4mm). 2 talismanic drawings. Verso: [different hand] 24 lines of text. (Box 1)
  Originally a large composition [now partly lost] of a transverse cross with an angel in the right-hand quadrant, and a cross and two figures in the bottom quadrant. (In ink with red and faded yellow color.)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with red and yellow wash.) The 5 lines of text above the figure are a sälam to the archangel Michael. There are also two decorative bands inserted within the text.
  Owner: the original owner's name, Wäldä Heywät (m.) has been overwritten with that of Wäldä Mika'él (m.)
  - The Secret Names of Solomon (Asmatä Sälomon), i.e. the Text Also Known as the Net of Solomon (Märbäbtä Sälomon), early 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against 'Tormenters and Enchanters', early 19th century; 1 item
  - Text Entitled the Secret Names of Solomon (Asmatä Sälomon), early 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Evil Demons and Evildoers, early 19th century; 1 item
    Untitled.
  - The Secret Names of the Trinity (Asmatä Sellasé), early 19th century; 1 item
  - Untitled Prayer Against, Inter Alia, Falling Into Chasms, Barya, Noontide Devils, Fever, etc, early 19th century; 1 item
  - Untitled Prayer against Devils, Evil Spirits, "Red and Black Barya," Buda and Sorcerers, early 19th century; 1 item
  - Confirmation of Faith in One God and the Trinity. Secret or Magic Names for the Confounding, Confusing and Frightening of Evil Demons, early 19th century; 1 item
  - Land Sale Record, circa 1855-1868; 1 item
    Verso.
    Dated in the reign of Téwodros II r. 1855-1868, 'Year Of Luke, 26th Day of Hedar'
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 29, late 19th century; 29; 1 box 2 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an uneven hand (5mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 2 talismanic drawings. 1220 x 90mm (Box 1)
  Contains the legend of Susenyos for the protection of infants and women with child.
  Schematic figure of a guardian angel. (In black ink with red and yellow color.)
  Cross with decorated arms set against a striated ground. (In black ink with red and yellow color.)
  A decorative band at the bottom of the scroll contains the text, 'for there is nothing of which Michael is incapable.'
  Owner: Feqertä Mika'él (f.)
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 30, 1830-1870; 30; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together; the top of the scroll is slightly damaged. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable sloping hand (4mm), framed between a linear border drawn in red and colored yellow. 2 talismanic drawings, 1 small ink sketch and 1 decorative band. (Box 1)
  Grid of 20 squares with alternate lines of rosette and transverse cross designs. (In ink with faded red and yellow color.)
  Grid of 9 squares with alternating faces, transverse cross, and rosette designs. (In ink with faded red and yellow color.)
  There are also two colored decorative bands and an uncolored sketch in ink of a hand cross.
  There is a further uncolored decorative band on the obverse.
  Owner: the original owner's name has been partially erased and replaced with that of Wälättä Yohannes (f.)
  - Prayer against Mäggañña and Shotälay, Followed by the Prayer and Legend of Susenyos for the Protection of Infants and Pregnant Women, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Successful Pregnancy, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage; Prayer against Colic, Mäggañña and Shotälay, mid 19th century; 1 item
    First prayer contains an extract from the Gospel of Mark.
  - Prayer against 'Devices and Spells' (Kin Wäseray), mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Buda and Blacksmiths, mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 31, 1870-1899; 31; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together, with a small parchment strip for tying at the top. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable hand (4mm), framed between an uncolored linear border. 2 talismanic drawings and 1 chart. (Box 1)
  Eight-pointed star. (In ink with yellow and purple color.)
  Cross (In ink with yellow, purple and blue wash color.) Grid chart (in red ink) of 15 squares containing letters, together with a number of magic letters (harägawi fidäl) outside the grid.
  Owner: the original owner's name has been erased and replaced with that of Bäsher Afléñ (m.)
  - Prayer for Binding of Demons and "Making Buda Speak", late 19th century; 1 item
  - Sälam (Hymn of Salutation) to the Archangel Phanuel, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Headache and Colic. 5, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Undoing of Spells, late 19th century; 1 item
    In continuo from preceding text
  - Prayer for Binding Evil Spirits and Malicious Demons, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Jaundice, the Evil Eye (Aynä T'ela) and Gärgari (lit. the Opponent ?), late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Jaundice and the Evil Eye, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Rheumatism, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye (Aynät), late 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 32, 1870-1899; 32; Single piece of parchment forming the bottom part of a complete scroll. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a mediocre hand (3-4mm). 2 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  Incomplete.
  Grid of 9 squares with a central face and alternate rosette and transverse cross designs. (Colored in red, blue and acid yellow.)
  A hand cross design set within a frame. (Colored in red, blue and acid yellow.) The accompanying text reads 'for thy maidservant Wälättä Musé.'
  Owner: Wälättä Musé (f.)
  - Conclusion of a Prayer against Shotälay, late 19th century; 1 item
    In abrupto.
  - Prayer for Subduing Enemies and Demons, Also against Shotälay, Barya and Légéwon, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against "The Enemy of Good and for [Women] Whose Children Die", late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer, Bismilahi Wälehadi Awälä Alani'animin Lämet'uhesh Réma, late 19th century; 1 item
    Untitled. Text, written wholly in red, is in what purports to be Arabic.
  - Prayer against Buda and Blacksmiths, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Conception and Childbirth, late 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 33, 1870-1899; 33; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an untutored and dense hand (5mm), framed within a simple uncolored border. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  A regal figure, perhaps Solomon, with two attendants. (In ink with pale red, blue-grey and yellow color.)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with pale red, blue-grey and yellow color.)
  Cruciform design comprising a central face (a cherub ?) and four faces as the arms of the cross, with four circles in the spaces between the arms. (In ink with pale red, blue-grey and yellow color. Above the figure is the text, 'the word of God shall extinguish the flames of fire.'
  Owner: the original owner's name, Gäbrä Mika'él (m.), has been overwritten with that of Wälättä Gäbre'él (f.)
  - Prayer for Exorcising Evil Spirits from the Possessed, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Repudiating Satan, etc, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Demons and the Evil Eye of Barya, Incorporating a Sälam (Hymn of Salutation) to the Archangel Phanuel, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Undoing spells. Prayer for Binding Demons, Zar, the Evil Eye of "Evil and Accursed" Barya, etc, late 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 34, 1800-1850; 34; 4 pieces of parchment sewn together; the top of the scroll is damaged and partly missing. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a small, reasonable hand (2mm). 3 full talismanic drawings, 1 chart and 1 partial drawing (at the damaged top of the scroll.) (Box 1)
  [at the damaged top of the scroll] the decorative band forming the base of a drawing. Grid of 9 squares with alternate infill of faces and lobed transverse cross designs formed of eye motifs. (In ink with black, red and yellow color.)
  [beneath no. 2] A grid of 20 squares each filled with a single letter. A cross in hand cross form, with two smaller crosses either side and two circles above; the whole is surrounded by small circles and there are some magic letters (harägawi fidäl) below. (In ink with black, red and yellow color.)
  Eight-pointed star design with a central face; the whole is amplified by further decorative arms giving the impression of a radiant sun. (In ink with black, red and yellow color.)
  Owner: the original owner's name, Qeddest Hanna (f.) is mostly erased and replaced with that of Gäbrä Rufa'él (m.)
  - Prayer against Possession by Spirits, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer for Undoing Spells and Charms, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer for Successful Childbirth, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer "Of the Strong and the Pregnant" (S'enu'an Wäs'enusat), for the Protection of Pregnant Women, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 35, 1800-1899; 35; incomplete]2 pieces of parchment sewn together; the top piece is now missing. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable hand, now much faded and partly illegible (3mm). 2 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  Large design composed of three vertically conjoined eight-pointed star motifs, each with a central face. The arms of the "stars" are reduced to series of triangles alternately left blank or filled with simple zigzag lines. (In ink with some red color and traces of yellow.
  Four decorated bands with latticework, chevron, transverse cross and rosette motifs.
  Owner: Wälättä Tensa'é (f.) ?
  - Prayer and Legend of Susenyos, 19th century; 1 item
    End.
  - Prayer against Shotälay and Mäggañña, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Binding of Demons, Incorporating a Sälam (Hymn Of Salutation) to Phanuel, 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 36, 1830-1870; 36; 2 pieces of parchment sewn together. 2 cols., written in black with rubrics in an uneven hand (2-4mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow with occasional zigzag design and separated by a margin of the same. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  A regal figure with two attendants (King Solomon ?). (In ink with greyish blue, red-brown and yellow color.)
  Grid of 35 squares variously with lobed transverse cross or simple transverse cross infill. (In ink with red-brown, yellow, black and blue-grey color infill.)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (in ink with red-brown, yellow, black and blue-grey color.)
  Owner: the original owner's name, Wäldä Abbiy (m.) is mostly overwritten with that of Wälättä Abbiyä Egzi' (f.)
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Drowning of Demons, mid 19th century; 1 item
    Comprises mostly secret names (asmat).
  - Prayer of Susenyos "Which Protects against Hemorrhage, Shotälay, Barya, Lägéwon [sic] ..", mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Driving Out Evil Spirits, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for General Protection, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya. Sälam (Hymn of Salutation) to Phanuel, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Rheumatism or (Chest) Pain (Weg'at), mid 19th century; 1 item
  - [beneath Drawing 3, 1 col.] Prayer in Amharic Addressed to St. Täklä Haymanot, mid 19th century; 1 item